A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Grants, Accession 2015:094 FA1409
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Grants, Accession 2015:094
1936-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1409
3.42 Cubic Feet 9 document containers
Related Materials
Most of the material in this collection has been microfilmed and corresponds with material found in the following Ford Foundation microfilm collections:
(Note: When searching for corresponding microfilm material, Program Action (PA) numbers in this collection are typed or handwritten on Ford documents in the following format: 55-123 (year)-(####). However, the Ford Foundation's grants database (LINKS) uses an 8-digit format for PA numbers: 05500123 (0YY#####). The materials in the microfilm collections are searchable in the 8-digit format)
FA732A Ford Foundation records, Grants, A-B
FA732B Ford Foundation records, Grants, C-D
FA732D Ford Foundation records, Grants, H-K
FA732E Ford Foundation records, Grants, L-N
FA732F Ford Foundation records, Grants, O-R
FA732G Ford Foundation records, Grants, S-Thel
FA732H Ford Foundation records, Grants, Them-Tw
FA732I Ford Foundation records, Grants, U-Z
More information relating to individual grants can be found in these collections' additional description notes.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains grant approval letters, correspondence, financial information, reports, and clippings related to Ford Foundation grants from 1936-1977.
General
Most folders contain the following note from March 1980:
This is a grant* made during the period 1936-1952. The following documents are the only records known for this grant action. The files kept for grants given at this time were maintained by the Treasurer in alphabetic order by institution. This grant file, like the others of this period, was assigned a Program Action (PA) number under which it has been microfilmed.
In some cases the "grant" was only a donation to a particular charity, society, or cause.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2015 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2015:094.
Arts; Charity; Cold War; Ford Foundation; Hospitals; schools; World War II
- Grant Files, 1936-1977; 1
  - PA 36-234 - Edison Institute, 1936-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Scope and Contents
    Ford Grant #03600234
    Grant Purpose: Construction and operating costs and purchase of antiques
    Grant Amount: $1,935,000.00;$13,852,500.00
    Also includes the documentation for other Edison Institute Grants 05100009 and 05100015
  - PA 36-235 - Henry Ford Hospital, 1936-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Grant #03600235
    Grant Amount: $985,000.00
    Grant Purpose: General Support
  - PA 37-53 - American Red Cross, 1937-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Grant #03700053
    Grant Purpose: Flood relief
    Grant Amount: $10,000.00
    Also contains documentation for other American Red Cross grants #04200062 and #04500054
  - PA 37-261 - Museum of Modern Art, 1937-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Grant #03700261
    Grant Purpose: Building Fund
    Grant Amount: $100,000.00
    Also contains documentation for Museum of Modern Art Grant #03800260
  - PA 37-263 - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, Inc., 1937-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Grant #03700263
  - PA 38-31 - American Federation of Arts, Inc., 1938-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Grant #03800031
    Grant Amount: $400.00
  - PA 38-241 - Goodwill Industries, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Grant #03800241
    Grant Amount: $1,500.00
  - PA 38-249 - Howard Street Mission, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Grant #03800249
    Grant Purpose: Building Purchase
    Grant Amount: $100.00
    Also contains documentation for Howard Street Mission Grant #04100250
  - PA 39-274 - The Seeing Eye, Inc., 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Grant #03900274
    Grant Amount: $4,900.00
  - PA 40-277 - United Foundation, Inc., 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Grant #04000277
    Grant Amount: $1,221,800.00
  - PA 41-187 - Detroit Symphony Orchestra, Inc., 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Grant #04100187
    Grant Amount: $37,500.00
  - PA 41-202 - Farmers Federation Educational and Development Fund, Inc., 1941-1950 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    Grant #04100202
    Grant Amount: $35,000.00
    Also contains documentation for Grant #04400200
  - PA 41-252 - Roscoe B. Jackson Memorial Laboratory, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Grant #04100252
    Grant Amount: $32,500.00
  - PA 41-254 - Merrill-Palmer School, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Also includes documentation for PA 52-81 and PA 56-11
  - PA 41-279 - United Service to China, Inc. (Formerly United China Relief), 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Grant #04100279
    Grant Amount: $7,000.00;$7,000.00
  - PA 41-67 - Antioch College of Yellow Springs, 1942-1949 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - PA 42-84 - Berea College, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Grant #04200084
    Grant Amount: $2,000.00;$2,000.00
    Also contains documentation for Grant #04500100 and Grant #04700105
  - PA 42-139 - The Detroit Institute of Arts, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Grant #04200139
    Grant Purpose: Publishing the Art Quarterly
    Grant Amount: $65,394.00;$65,394.00
    See PA 52-11 (Grant #05200011) and Fund File A for subsequent proposals and correspondence; PA 42-139 contains documentation for PA 48-138 (Grant #04800138)
  - PA 42-238 - Frontier Nursing Service, 1942-1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Grant #04200238
    Grant Amount: $9,000.00;$9,000.00
    Also contains documentation for PA 48-236 (Grant #04800236) and PA 50-237 (Grant #05000237)
  - PA 42-240 - Army Emergency Relief, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Grant #04200240
    Grant Amount: $1,000.00;$1,000.00
  - PA 42-265 - Navy Relief Society, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Grant #04200265
    Grant Amount: $5,000.00;$5,000.00
  - PA 43-65 - American Psychiatric Association, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - PA 43-66 - American Women's Voluntary Services, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Grant #04300066
    Grant Amount: $250.00;$250.00
  - PA 43-125 - Boys' Clubs of America, Inc., 1943-1950 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - PA 43-130 - Children's House, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Grant #04300130
    Grant Amount: $14,500.00;$14,500.00
  - PA 43-203 - Father Flanagan's Boys' Home, 1943-1951 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Grant #04300203
  - PA 43-262 - National Anti-Syphilis Committee (American Social Hygiene Association), 1942-1949 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Grant #04300262
    Grant Amount: $1,000.00
  - PA 43-278 - United Seamen's Service, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Grant #04300278
  - PA 43-282 - Wayne University, 1942-1949 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Grant #04300282
    Grant Purpose: Teacher Aviation Education Program
    Also contains documentation for PA 46-281 (Grant #04600281)
  - PA 44-52 - American Foundation for the Blind, Inc., 1942-1949 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Grant #04400052
    Grant Amount: $11,000.00
    Includes letters from Helen Keller
  - PA 44-199 - Diocese of Michigan, 1943-1950 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Grant #04400199
    Grant Amount: $25,000.00
    Also contains documentation for PA 47-198 (Grant #04700198)
  - PA 44-253 - Knights of Columbus, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Grant #04400253
    Grant Purpose: Service Men's Club
  - PA 44-258 - Michigan State Highway Department, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Grant #04400258
    Grant Purpose: Foundation Real Estate Deeded
    Grant Amount: $142,354.00
  - PA 44-285 - National Board of the Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A., 1943-1950 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Grant #04400285
    Grant Amount: $40,000.00
  - PA 45-10 - American Cancer Society, Inc., 1944-1950 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Grant #04500010
    Grant Amount: $25,000
  - PA 45-94 - Bon Secours Hospital, Inc., 1942-1951 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Grant #04500094
    Grant Amount: $2,500.00
  - PA 45-136 - Detroit Bureau of Governmental Research, Inc., 1944-1950 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Grant #04500136
    Grant Amount: $7,000.00
  - PA 45-162 - University of Detroit, 1944-1949 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Grant #04500162
    Grant Amount: $13,500.00
    Also includes documentation for PA 45-165 (Grant #04500165) and PA 45-193 (Grant #04500193)
  - PA 45-188 - Detroit Tuberculosis Sanatorium, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Grant #04500188
    Grant Amount: $200.00
  - PA 45-196 - Detroit Young Men's Christian Association, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Grant #04500196
    Grant Purpose: Rehabilitation of buildings and liquidation of indebtedness
    Grant Amount: $125,000.00
  - PA 45-245 - Hamtramck Tau Beta Camp Fund, 1944-1950 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    Grant #04500245
    Grant Purpose: Construction of a dam
    Grant Amount: $5,000.00
    Also includes documentation for PA 50-246 (Grant #05000246)
  - PA 45-256 - The Michigan Society for Epileptic Children, Inc., 1944-1949 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - PA 45-264 - National Recreation Association, Inc., 1945 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    Grant #04500264
  - PA 45-267 - Old Newsboys' Goodfellow Fund, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    Grant #04500267
    Grant Amount: $1,600.00
  - PA 45-272 - St. Vincent's Hospital, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - PA 45-273 - The Seaman's Church Institute, 1944-1948 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - PA 45-280 - The United Urban League Service Fund, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    Grant #04500280
    Grant Amount: $7,500.00
  - PA 46-19 - American Chinese Mass Education Movement, 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    Grant #04600019
    Grant Amount: $50,000.00
    Includes Section 5: Grant Attachments
  - PA 46-244 - Greenfield Congressional Church, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - PA 46-247 - Hindman Settlement School, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - PA 46-283 - The Wayside Inn, 1945-1952 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    Grant #04600283
    Grant Amount: $150,000.00
  - PA 47-97 - Children's Hospital of Michigan, 1947-1951 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    Grant #04700097
    Grant Purpose: General Rehabilitation Program
    Grant Amount: $2,000.00
    Also contains documentation for PA 50-122 (Grant #05000122)
  - PA 47-271 - St. Joseph Catholic Church, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    Grant #04700271
    Grant Purpose: Foundation real estate deeded
    Grant Amount: $12,435.00
  - PA 49-109 - Berry School, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - PA 49-194 - Detroit University School & Grosse Pointe Country Day School Corporation, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - PA 50-242 and PA 50-243 - Greater Detroit Hospital Council, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 58-59)
    Grant #05000242
    Grant Amount: $6,000.00
  - PA 50-257 - Michigan Society for Mental Hygiene, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    Grant #05000257
  - PA 50-270 - Protestant Children's Home, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    Grant #05000270
    Grant Purpose: Construction of a new building
    Grant Amount: $75,000.00
  - PA 51-13 - Committee of Hospital Trustees on Reimbursable Costs, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    Grant #05100013
    Grant Purpose: Reduce hospital costs of charity cases
    See also PA 50-242
  - PA 51-14 - Detroit Symphony Orchestra, Inc., 1951-1954 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    Grant #05100014
    Grant Amount: $30,000.00
  - PA 51-16 - The Harper Hospital, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    Grant #05100016
    Grant Purpose: Civil Defense Hospital Plan
    Grant Amount: $2,400.00
  - PA 51-17 - International Institute of Metropolitan Detroit, Inc., 1951 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    Grant #
    Grant Purpose: To develop USA citizenship of foreign born persons
  - PA 51-18 - Dearborn Public Schools, 1951-1969 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - General Information about 11 East European Fund Grants from April 1951 - February 1954 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    The 11 Grant Numbers include PA 51-22 (Grant #05100022), PA 51-40 (Grant #05100040), PA 52-73 (Grant #05200073), PA 52-107 (Grant #05200107), PA 53-190 (Grant #05300190), PA 53-201 (Grant #05300201), PA 53-31 (Grant #05300031), PA 53-31A, PA 54-169 (Grant #05400169), PA 54-11 (Grant #05400011), PA 54-11A
    The East European Fund was the Free Russia Fund from April 1951-October 1951
  - PA 51-22 - East European Fund, Inc. Research on U.S.S.R. & Orientation of Recent Soviet Emigres, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    Grant #05100022
    Grant Amount: $200,000.00
  - PA 51-40 - East European Fund, Inc. Research on U.S.S.R. & Orientation of Recent Soviet Emigres, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    Grant #05100040
    Grant Amount: $585,000.00
  - PA 52-11 - The Detroit Institute of Arts Magazine "The Art Quarterly", 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    Grant #05200011
    Grant Amount: $17,500.00
    See also PA 42-139 (Grant #04200139)
  - PA 52-12 - United Foundation, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    Grant #05200012
  - PA 52-73 - East European Fund, Inc. Research on U.S.S.R., Chekhov Publishing House, Displaced Persons General Administration, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    Grant #05200073
    Grant Purpose: GENERAL SUPPORT (INCLUDES $523,000 FOR CHEKHOV PUBLISHING HOUSE)
    Grant Amount: $785,000.00
  - PA 52-81 - General Support to the Merrill-Palmer School, 1951-1954 (Box 5, Folder 73-74)
    See also: PA 47-254 and PA 56-11
  - PA 52-85 - Organization for the Creation of Peace, 1951-1961 (Box 5, Folder 75-77)
    Foundation-Administered Project (FAP) - Conditions of Peace Project (05290085)
    Cross reference with Council on Foreign Relations PA 53-84
  - PA 52-107 - East European Fund, Inc. Economic Assistance for Administrative Expenses, 1952-1953 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    Grant #05200107
  - PA 52-114 - American Red Cross (Detroit Chapter, Tornado & Flood Relief), 1952 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    Grant #05200114
  - PA 52-115 - United Foundation, Inc., 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    Grant #05200115
    Grant Purpose: Administrative Survey
  - PA 52-118 - University of Chicago, 1952-1972 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - PA 52-150 - M.I.T., 1952-1968 (Box 6, Folder 82-85, Box 7, Folder 86, 87, 87A, 88)
    Note from cross reference sheet - (Formerly A-835) The early grants to MIT overlap extensively. Several reports that could not be located in this file may be found in others. This file covers the years 1951-1956 (with correspondence to 1967) while the subsequent grant PA 56-104 covers the period 1956-1977.
  - PA 53-31 - East European Fund, Inc. Research on U.S.S.R. Project, 1953-1954 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    Grant #05300031
    Grant Purpose: Support of program and in particular its program of educational and assistance to exiled groups and administration
    Grant Amount: $558,000.00
  - PA 53-190 - East European Fund, Inc. Research on U.S.S.R. Cultural Aspects, etc., 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    Grant #05300190
    Grant Amount: $666,000.00
  - PA 53-201 - East European Fund, Inc. Literary, Scientific, Educational Activities, etc., 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    Grant #05300201
  - PA 53-208 - United Foundation, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 92)
    Grant #05300208
  - PA 539-226 - Conduct of Governmental Affairs, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 93)
    Foundation Administered Project (FAP)
    Grant #05390226
    Grant Purpose: Conduct of governmental affairs
    Grant Amount: $10,518.00
  - PA 54-11 - East European Fund, Inc., 1954 (Box 8, Folder 94)
    Grant #05400011
    Grant Amount: $245,000.00
  - PA 54-152 - United Foundation, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    Grant #5400152
    Grant Purpose: General support
  - PA 54-169 - East European Fund, Inc. Support Chekhov Publishing House, 1952-1972 (Box 8, Folder 96)
    Grant #05400169
    Grant Purpose: Support of Chekhov Publishing House
    Grant Amount: $615,000.00
  - PA 56-11 - General Support to the Merrill-Palmer School, 1954-1962 (Box 8, Folder 97-99)
    See also PA 47-254 and PA 52-81
  - PA 56-104 - M.I.T., 1955-1977 (Box 9, Folder 100-102)